Hi. I'm Kevin Allocca, I'm the trends manager at YouTube,
مرحبا. أنا كيفين ألوكا، أنا مدير التوجهات في يوتيوب،
and I professionally watch YouTube videos.
وأنا أشاهد فيديوهات اليوتيوب بطريقة احترافية.
It's true.
هذا صحيح.
So we're going to talk a little bit today about how videos go viral
إذن سنتحدث اليوم قليلا عن كيف تنتشر الفيديوهات فيروسيا
and then why that even matters.
ثم لماذا يهمنا الأمر.
We all want to be stars --
كلنا نريد أن نصير نجوما --
celebrities, singers, comedians --
مشاهير، مغنيين، كوميديين --
and when I was younger, that seemed so very, very hard to do.
وحين كنت أصغر سنا، كان الأمر يبدو صعب الإنجاز.
But now Web video has made it
لكن الآن فيديو الويب قد جعل من الممكن
so that any of us or any of the creative things that we do
أن أي واحد منا أو أيا من الأمور الإبداعية التي نقوم بها
can become completely famous
يمكن أن تصبح مشهورة للغاية
in a part of our world's culture.
كجزء من ثقافة عالمنا.
Any one of you could be famous on the Internet
وأحدكم قد يكون مشهورا على الأنترنيت
by next Saturday.
بحلول السبت المقبل.
But there are over 48 hours of video uploaded to YouTube
لكن هناك حوالي 48 ساعة من الفيديوهات ترفع إلى اليوتيوب
every minute.
كل دقيقة.
And of that, only a tiny percentage
ومن ذلك، فقط نسبة ضئيلة
ever goes viral and gets tons of views and becomes a cultural moment.
تنتشر فيروسيا وتحصل على أطنان من المشاهدات وتصير لحظة ثقافية.
So how does it happen?
حسنا كيف يحدث ذلك؟
Three things:
ثلاث أشياء:
tastemakers, communities of participation
صانعوا الأذواق، مجتمعات المشاركة المحلية
and unexpectedness.
والفجائية.
All right, let's go.
حسنا إذن، هيا بنا.
(Video) Bear Vasquez: Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
(فيديو) بير فاسكويز: أوه، يا إلهي. أوه، يا إلهي.
Oh, my God!
أوه، يا إلهي!
Wooo!
ووو!
Ohhhhh, wowwww!
أوو، ووو!
KA: Last year, Bear Vasquez posted this video
ك. أ: نشر بير فاسكويز هذا الفيديو في السنة الماضية
that he had shot outside his home in Yosemite National Park.
والذي صوره خارج بيته في منتزه يوسمايت الوطني.
In 2010, it was viewed 23 million times.
في 2010، تمت مشاهدته 23 مليون مرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is a chart of what it looked like
هذا رسم بياني لما يبدو عليه
when it first became popular last summer.
حين صار شعبيا لأول مرة في الصيف الماضي.
But he didn't actually set out to make a viral video, Bear.
لكن بير لم يكن يريد أن يصنع فيديو ينتشر فيروسيا.
He just wanted to share a rainbow.
أراد فقط أن يشارك قوس قزح.
Because that's what you do when your name is Yosemite Mountain Bear.
لأن ذلك ما تفعله حين يكون اسمك دب جبل يوسمايت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he had posted lots of nature videos in fact.
وقد نشر الكثير من فيديوهات الطبيعة في الواقع.
And this video had actually been posted
وهذا الفيديو في الواقع تم نشره
all the way back in January.
في يناير السابق.
So what happened here?
إذن ما الذي حدث هنا؟
Jimmy Kimmel actually.
جيمي كيميل في الواقع.
Jimmy Kimmel posted this tweet
جيمي كيميل نشر تغريدة تويتر هذه
that would eventually propel the video to be as popular as it would become.
والتي ستقوم في الأخير بدفع الفيديو ليصير شعبيا كما هو الآن.
Because tastemakers like Jimmy Kimmel
لأن صانعي الأذواق مثل جيمي كيميل
introduce us to new and interesting things
يقدمون لنا أشياء جديدة ومثيرة
and bring them to a larger audience.
ويأتون بها إلى جمهور أوسع.
(Video) Rebecca Black: ♫ It's Friday, Friday. Gotta get down on Friday. ♫
(فيديو) ريبيكا بلاك: ♫ إنها الجمعة، الجمعة. يجب أن أنزل في الجمعة. ♫
♫ Everybody's looking forward to the weekend, weekend. ♫
♫ الجميع يتطلع إلى نهاية الأسبوع، نهاية الأسبوع. ♫
♫ Friday, Friday. Gettin' down on Friday. ♫
♫ الجمعة، الجمعة. النزول يوم الجمعة. ♫
KA: So you didn't think that we could actually have this conversation
ك. أ: لم تعتقدوا أننا قد نجري هذه المحادثة في الواقع
without talking about this video I hope.
دون الحديث عن هذا الفيديو على ما آمل.
Rebecca Black's "Friday" is one of the most popular videos of the year.
"جمعة" ريبيكا بلاك هو واحد من أكثر الفيديوهات شعبية هذه السنة.
It's been seen nearly 200 million times this year.
تمت مشاهدته لما يقارب 200 مليون مرة هذه السنة.
This is a chart of what it looked like.
هذا رسم بياني لما يبدو عليه.
And similar to "Double Rainbow,"
ومثل "قوس قزح المزدوج"،
it seems to have just sprouted up out of nowhere.
يبدو أنه ظهر إلى الوجود من لا مكان.
So what happened on this day?
إذن ماذا حدث في هذا اليوم؟
Well it was a Friday, this is true.
حسنا كان ذلك يوم جمعة، هذا صحيح.
And if you're wondering about those other spikes, those are also Fridays.
وإن كنتم تتساءلون عن تلك التموجات الأخرى، فهي ايضاً أيام جمعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what about this day,
لكن ماذا عن هذا اليوم،
this one particular Friday?
يوم الجمعة هذا تحديداً؟
Well Tosh.0 picked it up, a lot of blogs starting writing about.
حسنا Tosh.0 التقطه، الكثير من المدونات بدأت تكتب عنه.
Michael J. Nelson from Mystery Science Theater
مايكل ج. نيلسون من مسرح العلوم الغامضة
was one of the first people to post a joke about the video on Twitter.
كان أحد أول الناس الذين نشروا مزحة حول الفيديو في تويتر.
But what's important is that an individual or a group of tastemakers
لكن المهم هو أن شخصا أو جماعة من صانعي الأذواق
took a point of view
أخذوا وجهة نظر
and they shared that with a larger audience, accelerating the process.
وشاركوا ذلك مع جمهور أوسع، مسرعين عملية الانتشار.
And so then this community formed
وبالتالي تشكل هذا المجتمع
of people who shared this big inside joke
من الناس الذين تشاركوا هذه المزحة الكبيرة
and they started talking about it and doing things with it.
وبدأوا يتحدثون عنها ويقومون بأشياء بناءً عليها.
And now there are 10,000 parodies of "Friday" on YouTube.
والآن هناك 10,000 محاكاة ساخرة ل"الجمعة" على اليوتيوب.
Even in the first seven days,
حتى في الأيام السبعة الأولى،
there was one parody for every other day of the week.
كانت هناك محاكاة ساخرة لكل يوم آخر من الأسبوع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Unlike the one-way entertainment of the 20th century,
على خلاف التسلية الأحادية الوجهة في القرن ال20،
this community participation
هذه المشاركة المجتمعية
is how we become a part of the phenomenon --
هي كيف أصبحنا جزء من الظاهرة --
either by spreading it or by doing something new with it.
سواء من خلال نشرها أو القيام بشيء جديد لها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So "Nyan Cat" is a looped animation
إذن "قطة نيان" هي رسوم متحركة حلقية
with looped music.
بموسيقى حلقية.
It's this, just like this.
إنها تبدو هكذا .
It's been viewed nearly 50 million times this year.
تمت مشاهدتها لحوالي 50 مليون مرة هذه السنة.
And if you think that that is weird,
وإن كنتم تظنون أن هذا غريب،
you should know that there is a three-hour version of this
عليكم أن تعرفوا أن هناك نسخة من ثلاث ساعات من هذا
that's been viewed four million times.
تمت مشاهدتها أربع ملايين مرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Even cats were watching this video.
حتى القطط كانت تشاهد هذا الفيديو.
Cats were watching other cats watch this video.
القطط كانت تشاهد قططا أخرى تشاهد هذا الفيديو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what's important here
لكن ما هو مهم هنا
is the creativity that it inspired
هو الإبداع الذي ألهمه
amongst this techie, geeky Internet culture.
ضمن ثقافة مهووسي الانترنت و تقنياتها.
There were remixes.
كانت هناك ريمكسات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Someone made an old timey version.
أحدهم أنجز نسخة عتيقة.
And then it went international.
ثم صار لأمر عالميا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
An entire remix community sprouted up
مجتمع ريمكسات كامل ظهر
that brought it from being just a stupid joke
نقلتها من مجرد مزحة غبية
to something that we can all actually be a part of.
إلى شيء يمكننا جميعا أن نكون جزء منه.
Because we don't just enjoy now,
لأننا لا نستمتع به فقط كمستهلكين،
we participate.
بل نشارك فيه.
And who could have predicted any of this?
ومن كان ليتوقع أيا من هذا؟
Who could have predicted "Double Rainbow" or Rebecca Black
من كان ليتوقع "قوس قزح المزدوج" أو ريبيكا بلاك
or "Nyan Cat?"
أو "قطة نيان"؟
What scripts could you have written
أي برمجيات كنا لنكتب
that would have contained this in it?
لتتضمن هذا داخلها؟
In a world where over two days of video
في عالم حيث يومان من الفيديو
get uploaded every minute,
تُرفع كل دقيقة،
only that which is truly unique and unexpected
فقط المتميزة بحق والغير متوقعة منها
can stand out in the way that these things have.
يمكن أن تنتشر وتصمد مثل هذه الفيديوهات.
When a friend of mine told me that I needed to see this great video
حين أخبرني صديق أن علي رؤية هذا الفيديو الرائع
about a guy protesting bicycle fines in New York City,
حول شخص يحتج على غرامات الدراجات في مدينة نيويورك،
I admit I wasn't very interested.
أعترف أنني لم أكن مهتما جدا.
(Video) Casey Niestat: So I got a ticket for not riding in the bike lane,
(فيديو) كايسي نيستات: حسنا حصلت على مخالفة لأنني لم أركب الدراجة في ممر الدراجات،
but often there are obstructions
لكن عادة هناك عوائق
that keep you from properly riding in the bike lane.
تمنعنا من ركوب الدراجات كما يجب في ممر الدراجات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
KA: By being totally surprising and humorous,
ك. أ: بكونه مفاجئ ومضحكا بالكامل،
Casey Niestat got his funny idea and point
جعل كايسي نيستات جعل فكرته ووجهة نظره
seen five million times.
تُشاهد خمس ملايين مرة.
And so this approach holds
وبالتالي هذه المقاربة تبقى صالحة
for anything new that we do creatively.
لأي شيء جديد نقوم به بشكل إبداعي.
And so it all brings us
وبالتالي هذا يقودنا
to one big question ...
إلى سؤال كبير ...
(Video) Bear Vasquez: What does this mean?
(فيديو) بير فاسكيز: ما الذي يعنيه هذا؟
Ohhhh.
أوووه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
KA: What does it mean?
ك. أ: مالذي يعنيه هذا؟
Tastemakers, creative participating communities,
صناع الأذواق، المجتمعات الإبداعية المشاركة،
complete unexpectedness,
عنصر المفاجأة،
these are characteristics of a new kind of media and a new kind of culture
هذه هي مواصفات نوع جديد من الوسائط ونوع جديد من الثقافة
where anyone has access
حيث كل واحد يستطيع الوصول إليها
and the audience defines the popularity.
والجمهور يحدد الشعبية.
I mean, as mentioned earlier,
أقصد، كما ذكرت من قبل،
one of the biggest stars in the world right now, Justin Bieber,
أحد أكبر النجوم في العالم الآن، جستين بيبر،
got his start on YouTube.
كانت بدايته في يوتيوب.
No one has to green-light your idea.
لا أحد عليه إعطاء الضوء الأخضر لفكرتك.
And we all now feel some ownership
وكلنا نحس الآن بنوع من الملكية
in our own pop culture.
في ثقافة البوب الخاصة بنا.
And these are not characteristics of old media,
وهذه ليست خصائص الوسائط القديمة،
and they're barely true of the media of today,
وهي بالكاد تنطبق على الوسائط اليوم،
but they will define the entertainment of the future.
لكنها ستُشكّل تسلية المستقبل.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم،
(Applause)
(تصفيق)